Today we are launching
a major new program
by Gazprom,
the large-scale development
of the Kharasavey gas field,
in the Yamal peninsula.
The world of energy is a fascinating one.
Perhaps because people are capable of the worst in order to get into it.
Who gets hold of energy gets hold of power.
In today's world,
Russia is the largest gas producer.
Yamal contains 80%
of Russia's reserves.
And at this gas-safe deposit box,
I met the Nenets.
The Nenets are born in nature,
we are part of nature.
Without reindeer,
a Nenet is no longer a Nenet.
Will the Nanettes survive gas development?
Will their way of life suffer?
What's the impact on their environment?
In Yamal,
the Nanettes perpetuate from generation to generation the longest transhuman's route in the world.
Scattered in some 50 brigades,
called so since the Soviet era,
the Nanets live entirely off their livestock,
reindeer meat and skins.
In the tundra,
I followed two brigades,
number one and number four.
Every day of our life
depends on the weather.
We are constantly
searching for lichen,
and that is what spurs
our migration.
Vasili Seroteto is the patriarch of Brigade Number One.
He guides his herd of over 2,000 reindeer during a heroic journey.
In the Nenets language,
Yamal means the end of the world.
The Siberian peninsula located north of the Arctic Circle is 700 kilometers long,
a quarter of the surface of France.
From spring onwards,
the Nenets lead their herds to the north on the shores of the Kara Sea.
They search for the fresh air and rich pastures of the tundra.
In winter they head south through the frozen Ob,
one of the largest Russian rivers.
They leave the tundra for the taiga,
the boreal forest.
The tundra is everything to me.
We migrate
towards the Kara Sea.
We are sometimes on the move
for three days in a row.
We rest for a day,
then we travel
three days in a row.
We will continue to migrate.
It's the only life I know.
It all started 50 years ago when Soviet geologists made a discovery that would change the lives of the Nenets.
The Kharasavey gas field
was discovered in 1974.
APA
By the following year,
it was designated
objective number one
in the Yamal Peninsula.
Work was undertaken
with enthusiasm.
The permafrost
and the icy Arctic winds
caused the drillers and builders
serious problems.
The works got bogged down
and were abandoned in 1981.
The Yamal Peninsula
was beyond the reach of the USSR.
They built this drilling platform
in 1982.
They were looking for gas
and they found it.
In 1984,
they built a port.
It lasted a year.
As the bay
wasn't deep enough,
they decided
to dig a canal.
Following a storm
and flooding,
everything was submerged.
You see,
nature does not tolerate that.
She floods everything.
The fruit of two weeks of work
was swept away by nature
in just one night.
It happens.
Nothing discourages the Russian authorities,
neither the complexity of gas exploitation,
nor the extreme climate conditions of Yamal.
Industrialization can start.
For generations,
Brigade No.
4 passed through the Bovenenkovo area,
now the dominion of Gazprom,
the heart of gas exploitation.
Over the years,
Mian Gehudi has seen the tundra change dramatically.
When I was your age,
my father and grandfather
migrated along this path.
They taught me the route.
One day, on this mound,
we spotted a covered sled.
They were geologists,
explorers searching for gas.
There used to be nothing here.
Look, son.
We would set up our camps
down there.
Those pipes weren't there.
Now we have
to pass under the pipes.
We used to migrate over there,
on dry land.
But it's getting difficult
to migrate these days.
Want to use the land and the towns are growing and
and and that is that is a real pressure
and there is no way to invent these pastures somewhere else.
When I was 17,
I saw machines
drilling for gas.
Everything was covered in sand.
They were prospecting
all over the place.
I saw reindeer tracks
covered in sand.
I thought:
"If I don't educate myself,
I won't be able
to help my parents.
To ensure the reindeer tracks
don't disappear,
I decided to study.
Alec
Seroteto, son of Vasili,
is one of the few Nenets to have graduated with diplomas in law and economics.
He lives in Yars Sali,
in a small town in southeastern Yamal.
I cannot speak for everyone,
only for my community,
my parents,
my brothers.
I bear the responsibility
of being the one who studied.
My role is to help them,
to defend their interests.
It is a great responsibility.
I am an independent contractor.
I have my own business.
I worked in administration
for eight years.
I was a fervent political advocate
for the interests
of the indigenous peoples.
I stood up
to the oil and gas company.
was too independent
for their taste
and so, in 2011,
they fired me.
There is growing interest
for the Arctic in the world
and it is a priority for Russia.
The development of Russian
infrastructure projects in the Arctic
has begun,
and is actively continuing.
Every year Russia organizes an international conference on the oil and gas industry in St.
Petersburg.
The entire Russian state elite and apparatus have a single objective
to become the world's leading energy power.
You probably know
that over 80%
of natural gas reserves
and over 20% of oil
are concentrated in the Arctic zone.
The Arctic projects
are a priority for us.
The gas extraction process
involves the construction
of infrastructure.
Before extraction of the gas,
the land has to be prepared,
sand has to be found, digging done.
Water is needed.
Much land becomes
unavailable for grazing
to make way
for drilling machinery.
The preparatory works
cause us many problems.
They will extract the gas
until there is none left.
That will take
another 50 to 100 years
Villages are changing into city such as Saleharlt
or into dormitory towns like Bovonenkovo.
Infrastructure is expanding.
Gazprom is building the world's most northerly railway line.
And Novatec,
together with Total,
build an industrial exploitation site.
So better.
They designed a harbour and an international airport with a direct connection to Moscow.
To date, Yamal is the zone
that we know best.
It offers an opportunity to access foreign markets.
The gas produced
on the Yamal Peninsula
has been supplied
to South and North America.
Almost all purchasing countries
have received
these gas molecules.
One of our current priority tasks
is to take advantage
of these opportunities.
In the West,
the Russians have built pipeline networks to transport gas overland into Europe.
In the East,
they open a northeastern seaway,
with Yamal as the point of departure.
LNG tankers filled with liquid gas are leaving for the West,
others towards Asia.
However,
from December to April,
this sea route around the Bering Strait is closed.
It is covered by more than three meters of thick ice.
It is a seaway
that opens us to the world.
It is our strength,
we want to transport gas to the East.
To do so,
we need powerful icebreakers.
If we take the route
via the Ob-Yenisei Canal,
to the Cape of Zhelaniya,
there are over 1000 km
of pack ice.
Lit
And it's 4,500 km
from Yamal to Cape Dezhnyov.
For the first time in history
the Northeast Russian route
will be a seaway
Nuclear ice-breaker criss-cross the ocean
to facilitate the 6000 km strach along the siberian coast
=
over the Arctic's raw materials.
Slacken it a little here
Vasili has only one concern,
the survival of his herd and his way of life.
Everything related to reindeer
is my responsibility.
If a chief mismanages
such a big brigade,
if he makes a mistake,
he cannot make up for it
over the course of the year.
If his preparations
for the summer are inadequate,
he will not succeed in that season.
After summer comes the fall.
If the chief doesn't work well
in the fall,
he'll have problems.
If nothing is ready,
time will be wasted.
We could get caught up
in the October snowstorms,
the reindeer could lose
the weight they gained in summer.
If we don't reach
the winter pastures early enough,
we're done for.
The reindeer won't gain weight.
But if we do get there in time,
we let them graze
like wild reindeer.
If they don't gain weight
during that period,
they'll be thin in spring
and won't bear offspring.
If I do my job badly,
I won't have top-quality meat
come the fall.
By 2024,
we plan to transport
80 million tons of goods
by the Northern Sea Route.
To maintain this level of traffic,
we need state-of-the-art icebreakers.
The transport of 80 million tons
makes this a requirement.
A major challenge for icebreakers is to open the seaways to tankers filled with liquefied gas.
They leave from the tip of the Ob River to reach Asia in 15 days,
instead of 30 via the Suez Canal.
The Arctic is no longer a sanctuary.
It is being transformed into some 5,500 kilometers long maritime highway.
Drifting ice
is a major problem for us.
We need to use some new tactics of ice navigation.
New type of work,
you know.
We have some experience with icebreaker assistance with small ships.
We know how to lead them,
we know how to tow them,
but with such a new type we don't know,
we don't have such experience.
And this is the most problem maybe nowadays.
Usually we can break about one and a half meters,
sometimes two meters,
we can go through this ICS.
Our main purpose is to lead the ship as an icebreaker.
We are going very close to the ship and we break the ice near the ship and that can help to start the move.
The main problem is that we can go through the ice,
but the question is if our ship could.
That ship that we are leading sometimes can't.
And if we can go through the ice but the ship which we lead can't,
the main purpose is not completed.
Up until now,
ten LNG tankers
were operating
in the Arctic Circle.
The plan is
to increase that number to 30
How do you think
you will assist 30 LNG tankers
not to mention
the other vessels?
Three first-class
nuclear icebreakers
will not be enough
for such an amount of work.
Obviously,
the Nenets are not happy.
Production has been launched.
It's inevitable.
They don't try to prevent it,
set it on fire,
or sabotage anything.
But they complain.
My own feeling is
that it's impossible to stop it.
The machine is launched,
and it's advancing.
The oil and gas industry
has been active for 30 years.
The transformation
must be reasonable,
so that it doesn't eradicate
that which has preceded it
for many centuries.
The main field
being worked today
is that in Bovanenkovo.
Sabetta-Yamal is operated
by Gazprom Dobycha Nadym.
Gazprom Neft Yamal operates
the Novyi Port field.
The gas leaves
from Mys Kamennyi
in tankers
and is transported abroad.
The icebreakers
patrol all year round.
They break the ice
for the tankers they assist.
In
the Gulf of the Ob,
the crossing is narrow.
The icebreakers are patrolling all the time.
The most difficult period
in the Gulf of Ob
is end of March, early April.
and is at its thickest.
The current width of the canal,
which has already been widened once,
is the minimum width
for us to be able to work there.
Two-way traffic is impossible
when the ice is that thick.
The LNG tanker
has to go first.
But we cannot maneuver freely
to go to the tanker's aid.
There's no room for maneuver
with a 280-meter long boat,
that much is clear.
The director of the
Murmansk shipyard declared
that the President has set a goal
of 800 commercial trips per year
for the Arctic fleet.
Can you imagine that?
800 trips in 365 days.
It will be non-stop.
In Seyakha, they shut down
the State Farm due to the constant fog
and passage of the icebreakers.
And when the tankers use
the Northem Sea Route,
they ballast with sea water,
then unballast here,
in the Ob estuary,
to load the hydrocarbons.
The composition of the water
has changed completely.
Last year,
in the village of Seyakha,
tap water turned salty.
There used to be 97 brigades
of reindeer herders.
Today, there's only
half that number.
We estimate that 60 to 70%
of the indigenous population
live under the poverty line,
even though the region
is so rich.
It's not normal.
Their way of dealing with the advancement of the gas industry is not taking a total opposition and saying we are going to defend our land against the gas industry because it can only happen in conflict.
They try to find ways in which they can continue their own lifestyle in spite of having the gas industry on their land.
And if Moscow says that that deposit is going to be developed,
these people are not stupid.
They know that if Moscow says it,
it will be developed,
full stop.
This industry is too big a thing.
The Nenets wouldn't be able to resist it completely.
They wouldn't be able to veto it,
because they don't have the rights to do that.
There's no way they can say,
oh,
we don't want the Bovinenkova deposit to be extracted.
They can have something to say about smaller issues,
and I think this dedication to the smaller issues is what rescued a lot of the lifestyle that we can still see today.
The reindeer and the Nenets
are as one.
It's innate.
We live in symbiosis
with nature.
In the e tundra,
there's no such thing as bad weather.
We work in all weather,
and in unison with the weather.
Nature is freedom.
Vika, your little brother's crying!
Come on, hurry up!
A swift girl, an agile girl..
Kolya, come here.
He's found something.
Shall I sew it from outside
or inside?
Won't you wear another coat?
- No.
So take it off
and tell me where it's torn.
The side of the mitten,
on the right.
In the tundra,
a man without a wife,
is no longer a man.
He cannot live without her.
But a woman
without a man,
say for example he dies,
will survive easily.
She knows how to do everything.
She cares for the reindeer.
She ensures there's heating,
cares for the children.
She can mount a tent
and migrate alone.
The most important thing
is to have support:
a brigade, or neighbors
who can  guide her.
She can follow them.
Yes, she can do everything.
But a man cannot live
without a woman.
He disappears immediately.
The gas flares burn,
the climate changes.
The extraction of gas
leads to a change in temperature.
Sometimes it's cold,
sometimes spring comes early,
sometimes too late.
Sometimes winter is milder.
All that is because
of gas extraction.
It didn't use to be like this.
Nature was intact.
They are destroying nature.
Where they are operating,
there are gas flares
and emissions.
It's impossible to live
near Bovanenkovo
Within a 25 km radius
there are smoke emissions
and ashes from flares.
The ashes fly around
and land on the ground.
There is no pasture land
within a 25 km radius.
Naturally,
Bovanenkovo is vast.
I have been there several times.
These days,
it's warmer there than here.
The geese arrive there earlier
than they do here
They follow a warm current,
the Gulf Stream.
When we get there
the geese have already arrived.
I don't know
what the future holds for us.
I don't have
the slightest idea.
Most of the hydrocarbons that are in the Arctic are located on the Russian side and those will be developed.
That's what's driving our current climate problem and so it's kind of ironic that obviously as the Arctic opens up and you can now start drilling and extracting more resources such as oil and gas and that's just going to further amplify the climate change that we're going through.
There is a lot of methane
in this region.
When it rains,
the water starts
to accumulate.
When the reindeer stamp on the ground,
it starts to move.
There is 50 cm of mud,
then sand,
and below that
is the permafrost.
You're warming the Arctic up so much faster and all the permafrost areas are thawing.
And that's going to affect all the plant species as well as the animal species in the Arctic as well.
The ice is melting faster,
the permafrost is thawing faster.
I mean,
all of these are interconnected.
It's just that there are traditional indicators of how they understand the climate system,
how they understand storms and ice conditions and species migration.
All of that is changing as a result of climate change,
because I think the pace that we're seeing today in the changes that are happening in the Arctic is so fast,
much faster than anything that's happened in the historical past.
So that's why their traditional ways of knowledge aren't working anymore.
The water used to go up
to the banks.
Now it has lowered
and the banks are visible.
It's now difficult to climb
with a loaded sled.
Many tip over.
Here, the current
is always the same.
When we head for the Kara Sea,
it's much stronger.
On this side of the river,
there is a lot of erosion
when it rains.
It's sandy and soft.
When it rains,
it erodes easily.
Sometimes,
we have to dig with spades
to allow the sled
to get up or down.
The descent must be feasible
and the climb doable.
He committed suicide after an oil and gas consultation with the company Amoco back in the
1990s.
After this,
he thought that that would be the end of the life for that group of reindeer nomads.
And he couldn't stand that.
It's really,
really nice also for his legacy to see that his son and his grandchildren are still moving on the same land.
It's the most complicated stretch.
Each brigade has
its own route and pastures.
We do not want
to disturb each other.
The constant sound of the gas flares
can even wake a heavy sleeper.
We have no choice,
we have to get used to it.
It's impossible to get to sleep,
but those who sleep deeply
feel like they're sleeping.
The winter of 2013-2014
was normal.
Then, suddenly, there was a thaw,
with fog and rain.
The snow started to melt.
The temperature rose to 5°C.
Then snowstorms came
from the north.
The temperature dropped
down to -25°C.
The reindeer couldn't reach
the lichen to feed.
There was packed snow
to that depth.
And half of that crust was ice.
The wind from the north
was very cold.
Nocturnal temperatures
dropped to -30°C.
During the day,
it rose to -25°C.
It was mid-April.
The reindeer started to disperse.
We hung on for the first
two or three days,
but on the fourth day,
the reindeer scattered.
Thanks to the work
of my sons Alik and Roman,
we brought them back together.
We managed to move them
to pastures
where there was more lichen.
That's how we held out
during that difficult time.
Some nights,
we barely slept.
We lost around 200 reindeer.
Some perished,
others escaped.
Without the help of our friends
living in the city,
we wouldn't have survived.
Several herds disappeared
and died of hunger.
There are times
when all you do is survive.
Yes, you have to hang in there.
In
the winter of 2014,
more than a quarter of the reindeer died in the Yamal Peninsula.
We're trying to regulate
the price of meat, which is too low.
I go round the administrations
to defend our budget.
On our migratory routes,
there are gas drilling stations
every 50-60 km.
Where can
the reindeer herders go?
They must go elsewhere.
We have money.
With this money,
we can set up programs
to support the herders.
Reindeer herding is
first and foremost a way of life,
it is a set of traditions,
a culture.
They supply meat
to the State,
which supports them
by buying it at 450 rubles the kilo,
a very good price.
The price in the shops
is lower
than what the State
pays the herders.
All summer
he gave me to believe
that the price of meat
would go up to 450 rubles,
and he encouraged me
to slaughter reindeer.
"What are you doing?
You're tricking people."
For five years, we have been
negotiating a rise in the price of meat
so that the herders
can make a decent living.
A document announces
that meat will soon cost 450 rubles.
But they will not buy it
at that price.
They say: "Herders,
slaughter your reindeer!"
They're doing it
to reduce the reindeer population.
They say they'll raise the price,
hoping it will incite herders
to slaughter more.
The villages get bigger,
which is probably good.
Yar-Sale is growing.
Gazprom's presence
spurs construction.
But for the reindeer herders,
there is nothing of interest.
It's a good thing
for children to be able to study.
Boarding schools are built
and Gazprom finances everything.
The boarding school system
came into being a long time ago.
Our grandparents already went
to boarding school.
It's part of our life now.
Even the last child
in the family
is sent to boarding school.
They can get an education.
adidas adidas
It's essential.
Modern reindeer herders
need to be educated.
They have to understand.
The reindeer will not disappear
in the 21st century.
Some of my grandchildren
will stay in the tundra
and raise reindeer.
Strength, endurance, speed,
I have all you need to be a herder.
I can catch reindeer,
I can fish.
I know how to survive.
If reindeer wander off,
you have to go and get them.
You have to be able
to find your way back.
One foggy day,
I got lost.
I was alone, I couldn't see
the camp and it was raining.
Another time,
I was looking after the herd on my own.
I did 30 km on a sled,
in the snow.
It took around 15 hours.
It worked out.
I used the moon and stars
to navigate,
and there were places
that I recognized.
I love to throw the lasso
to catch reindeer.
And then there's hunting.
It's impossible to put
these emotions into words.
I will stay here.
I want to migrate.
I want to live a nomadic life.
The tundra is everything to me.
Here, it's not like in the city.
There is freedom.
There is no noise,
no cars, no asphalt.
To live in town
or in the tundra?
That will be my decision
and mine alone.
But I would like
to live in town and work.
I would be able to help my family,
my nephews, my nieces
and my brothers.
I want to make their lives easier.
When I'm at boarding school,
the hardest thing
is waiting nine months
to see my parents.
And then to see them
only for a few days.
That's why I want
to stay in town.
If I lived in the tundra,
I would I be worried
for my future children.
How long would I have to wait
before I could see them?
It would be very complicated.
In the tundra,
children leave the camp for nine months.
This is the last summer morning.
Eynye, are you going
to wash your face?
Yes!
Vika, your little brother.
Take him!
Vika!
Tolik, take him!
Tolik!
Don't move.
Stop it, you're cold.
That's what I'm saying,
you have some coffee too.
We're not having any.
You're out of coffee!
Get dressed quickly,
I'll give it to you outside.
Vika, stand there.
Hurry, Vika,
the chopper's about to leave.
Kolya, look over here.
It's not the right chopper!
It's very hard.
Lots of people live together
in the tent,
and suddenly
our parents are all alone.
It's sad.
It's too quiet.
No more kids,
running all over the place.
And we think we'll wake up
in the tent with our family -
then we remember
that we're in town.
Stuck between four walls,
and our loved ones
are no longer there.
You tell yourself
that when you leave the tundra,
all will be well.
But you cry anyway.
It's impossible
not to be sad.
I realize
that I'll only see them again
in winter,
in many months' time.
11A
As always,
on September 1st
our family welcomes its new pupils.
Today, we have
202 new pupils.
Dear new pupils,
I wish you success.
Those who come from the tundra,
who have lived with their family,
in small communities,
find it a little hard at first,
because we have
over 1,500 children.
All of a sudden,
they're part of a big community,
and they have
to find their place.
It's always like that.
Is it Ilyushka?
- Yes.
Did you add bread to the meatballs?
Tolik's doing a back flip
in slow motion.
I took my phone too.
We said many goodbyes
to Théodore when he left.
He cried.
It's the first day
that the foreigners arrived.
Time flew by too fast.
- As always.
He did it on his own.
Tolik does it well.
What a champ!
Look.
What?
- Anti-stress.
Nadya?
Could you bring
an armful of firewood?
No one forces me
to do this,
but I feel
a sense of responsibility,
because I live here.
So I take them to my home
each weekend,
to get them away
from boarding school life,
to give them a home atmosphere
and good home cooking,
fish, meat, berries.
Over the two days
of the weekend,
they feel some of the comforts
of their tundra home.
In winter, we snowmobile,
in summer, we pick berries.
Afterwards, they can cope
with another week at school.
What shall we sing?
You're a bee,
I'm a beekeeper.
Ah, we love honey.
I'm going to be lucky.
I'm going to be lucky
with you.
It's important
that there be changes
for the young Nenets.
There are few Nenets
with university degrees.
As children
of herders in the tundra,
they are offered
a limited range of professions:
veterinarian,
zootechnician, or teacher.
Teachers and professors
who are not Nenet
consider these children
of the tundra
to have limited
cognitive capacities.
There is no interest
in improving the quality of education
to enable these young people
to go to university.
It's a vicious circle.
The nomadic life could disappear.
Today,
it is on the brink of survival.
It will either get worse,
or stagnate.
50 % of the population
will probably become sedentary.
What will the herders do
in the village, without reindeer?
My brothers
who live in the tundra
raise reindeer.
Will my brothers live in tents,
near Yar-Sale?
What will they do?
We will extract more and more
hydrocarbons from the ocean.
Should we engage in extraction
from the Arctic Shelves?
The answer is obvious:
yes, we must.
Gazprom is actively working on it.
Y
The Northern Sea Route
is actively being explored.
By 2050,
the Arctic Shelves
of Russia and other countries
be among the main suppliersof hydrocarbons
to world markets.
Like Vasili,
I don't know what tomorrow will bring,
facing both climate change and crazy gas extraction.
The Nanats will have to rely on their strengths,
their knowledge of nature,
and their capacity for resilience to survive,
as the backbone of which is the transhuman's route that they have walked for generations.
Nature is strong,
it recovers quickly.
It doesn't like damage,
it heals itself rapidly,
as a body does a wound.
For upcoming generations,
not much will change.
But gas is not inexhaustible,
it will run out.
After that, the earth will heal
and be even better than before